Do you know that since, what was I going to tell you
?  Since, no, since December of
last year, eh, we were working with
video lists and I got to December
and I saw that it was a mess and I couldn't
find my own videos, so I
say, if I, as the teacher, can't
find the videos, then I understand that
the students can't find them even less, okay?  So
last Christmas, I
made this app for myself, which
is kind of a medium green, and the thing is,
I found this app so useful that I
said, "Wow, if the students
find out I have this and I haven't
shared it, they're going to kill me, okay?"
Because, I mean, and I did, it started to
become super useful for finding out what
videos they had recorded every day, about what
subjects and such. And then click and
watch the video, so, uh, I don't know, I
don't know if it was in January, I don't
remember, but I told the students,
"Hey, entry here and such." Uh, at
first it was without a username, then I added a
username back in, I don't know, March, April, I
don't remember.
Okay, so, uh, like today, Thursday, is
when I'm recording my first
classes, okay?
Uh, of course, today the medium green
is still not updated.
The medium green right now, at this
moment, shows the content from
last year. If you look, okay? September
2024  It shows the content from
last year. So, Miguel Ángel was
kind of asking about
last year's content so he could
review or analyze or study or watch the
videos or whatever, okay?
And nothing, I mean, the answer is that the
content is here. Now, the question
is, the content is here and it's here.
There it is, already available. The question is,
what's going to happen now? What's going to
happen when, uh, from now on I start
uploading videos and therefore we
have to put the content from this
course here and not the content from the
previous course? What's going to happen? I don't know. I
have no idea. Why? Well, because I
've been thinking about two alternatives.
The first is that if we
get
to April 25 here,
okay? April, May, and so on, which is when
people went on internships,
then
here at the end of June 2025, I'll
put more months, that is, uh, July
2025, August, September, October,
November, okay? And then 202.
Another alternative
is that,  For example, here I put a
tab system where it says course 24
25 and when you click on it, it's in
last year's recordings, course 25 26 and when you click on it,
it's in this year's recordings.
Okay? I don't know which one I'm going to do, but
obviously I'll do one of the two. What
I mean is that not in the case
of Miguel Ángel, where it's to consult
last year's material, to catch
up or to get acquainted with the technologies
we're working on and all that, eh,
well, that's it, okay? And for those of you who were
last year's students, I'd like to
tell you that if it happens that I end up adding
tabs, don't think that I've
deleted last year's content,
just notice that there are
tabs and that's it, okay?
Hey, next question. Next
question. Hey, today is the
first class, okay? The
previous class was with Python, the
next class will be with Python. The class
we're going to do now will be with
Python. Uh, but for example, in the
calendar
this next week, oh,  Sorry,
backwards here. This next week, wait
a minute, let me clear things out. This
next week,
oh no, sorry, sorry, sorry. No,
no, tomorrow, tomorrow, tomorrow we have
business management systems.
Business management systems is the
hardest subject in second-year
DAM. It's the most important subject. And
there, as you can imagine, what
we're going to do is program a
business management system.
What will we program it in?
Well, I don't know. Okay? The
client side, obviously in HTML, CSS, and
JavaScript, because there's no other option.
The server side, what will we
do it in? I have no idea. Maybe in
Python and then we set up an engine
through Flask or maybe we do it in PHP. I
have no idea what we'll do it in,
okay? It's kind of the least of it.
So, the idea is that,
well, in each subject, we'll
work on some technologies, for
example, in multimedia programming, which we
'll start with
video game programming and then continue with
mobile programming. I'll show you the
Monday, the syllabus. Uh, of course, we'll
do video game programming
with JavaScript,
okay? And in interface development,
well, we'll probably be
working with a mix of HTML, CSS, and
JavaScript. That is, just like
last year, we're going to mix
different languages ​​so that in each
subject we can find the best, let
's say, of each of the languages.
Ultimately, the point is that
if you need to review, you should know
that you'll always have the content from
last year. Okay, that said,
let's start the
process and services course. And this course,
until recently, was a Maria. It was a
Maria for the following reason: Look, I go to
process and services programming and
I see that there are five teaching units where there is multiprocess programming, multithreading programming, what would be called multicore, which is really multithreading. Then, network communications programming, that is, programs that open a port on the network and communicate with other programs on the
network.
Creation of network services, for
example.  create a web server so we can
understand each other, okay? And use
secure programming techniques, since
we're going to communicate, well, we're going to
establish a series of
security measures, right? So that our
applications don't crash. Okay,
what's happening? I love all of this—this subject was all this—you'll
see now, but this subject
was very geeky, okay? It was a subject
about very geeky things, but
nevertheless, what's
happening next is that, as you know, we're
transitioning from the
information age to the age of
artificial intelligence, and in the age of
artificial intelligence,
multicore computing is key
because there's a lot to process,
and parallel processing is the key
to everything. So this subject has
gone from being a subject, María, that I've
always loved to teach,
but the students were like,
"What the hell is this for me, and
how am I going to get work from this if
this is so geeky?" Okay, but
the opposite has happened. In addition, it
happens that  At least at the moment,
in recent years, the technique that's in
fashion for training
artificial intelligence is Transformers. And
interestingly,
by chance, I'll tell you
why, Transformers is a
fully parallelizable technique,
that is, it consists of not just one
head, but several heads
processing the information, so
several heads are equivalent to several
cores in a computer. Let's start
working with this and let's
name things a bit.
Okay, so I'm going to go to, well,
I'm going to go here to Python
and I'm going to change to the subject of
processes and services.
Uh, services, processes, okay?
Multiprocess, executables, processes and
services.
Okay? What is an executable in this case?
Of course, what is an executable? Well,
in Python it's not executable, okay? In
Python it's a file that is interpreted
by the interpreter.
For example, a moment ago Miguel
Ángel was commenting on Java topics.
Well, we spoke on the phone. Java
doesn't generate an executable either, Java
generates a  byte code, that is, it generates an
intermediate file. Only in the case of
going down to C or C++,
because we would be talking about pure executables.
Okay,
I'm aware that last year the
C++ topic traumatized you quite a bit,
although it was a bit of an introduction.
So, I don't want you to start with C++ today, the first day
of the course,
because you'll surely abandon
the cycle, okay? And I don't want you to
abandon the cycle. We're going to start
gently, we're going to start
easily, we're going to start with Python and
later on we'll go into more
depth and we'll get into it and we'll
do more about everything.
Wait, I'm trying to turn off the
air conditioning. Oh,
dammit, I can't turn off the air
conditioning. Well, nothing, well I
'm going to freeze to death. Just a second, I'm going
to get up. Just
a second.
No, no, Fran, no, no, no way, it's a
trap. I'll tell you now. Give me a
second.
Well, nothing, well,
the batteries in the remote control have died,
so now I'm doomed to
have  the air conditioning until I
freeze to death. Okay? Hey, I was telling you, Fran,
right? Okay, what Python actually does
when generating Autopy to Exe is
a Windows Exe and that Exe has the
file, the Python script and the
interpreter right there, so
you don't need to download the
interpreter, but that's not generating a
real executable, it's generating a
hidden executable, where that
executable has the interpreter, okay?
But it's a package, let's say. When
we talk about an executable, I mean
a real executable, that is, a
C++ executable that generates a
platform-dependent executable binary, okay? I mean, a
cool executable. Python is cool for being able to
distribute applications and make it easy
and all, but okay, but it's not, let's say,
this is the case. Okay, let's see what a
process is. Hey,
what's up, man?
Why don't I have one?
Why don't I have
the folder?
Here it goes. Okay, so we're going to do 101
exercises
and that's it. Okay,
where  Are you? Here. I'm
uploading
exercises, okay? And 001 Python process.
Okay, if I do this, this thing that you
've seen me do more than once, for in
range from er to 10,000 million
trillion, I
'm going to, I'm creating a
hard control structure and equal to, no, sorry,
number equals 1.0098,
[Music]
okay? This exercise will sound like
last year. So I say, eh, number
equals 1.00 whatever. That is,
I'm forcing a hard calculation. That
means that print
I start
and print I finish.
F5. I start.
Maybe I went a little overboard, okay? But I
almost prefer it. I take out
the editor from the resource viewer
and I'll see that I have a core, although it is then
distributed, okay? But I have a
core there hammering away and I go to,
attention, look, processes tab and I
see that by CPU
there is a Python 3 process that is
taking up 6.30 and something%  of CPU.
Why a 6? Attention, everyone look at the
screen. This is very important because
if I divide 100 by 16, it gives me 6 and
something. Okay, look, it's over, it's
over, it's over, I'm done. I
mean, I'm going to do it again.
Attention, uh, Python takes up 0.03. But
if I do this,
look how Python will be. Where are you?
There it is.
So, why? Why 16? Sorry,
why 100/16?
Because 100% is what my
processor can handle, but I have 16 cores,
so that 100% is divided by 16.
And therefore, if I program a program
in Python
that is only capable of using one
process, that is, one processing thread
of the processor, at most it will use
6.31%.
See? And now it's going to go down. Now, boom, it
goes down to 0.65. Okay,
this is wrong
because if I  I have a
multi-core processor and I have 16 cores, what I
want is to create an application that
uses all 16 cores. I want to create
an application that uses 100% of the
processor. This first point of the
syllabus,
let's see, this first point of the
syllabus consists of generating executables,
okay? In the case that it were in C++,
because in no other language
can executables be generated.
In this case, we have seen that the
execution of a script generates a process,
even if it's the interpreter, okay?
We'll talk about services, where services
are a process that, instead of
running, doing a job, and stopping, what it
does is stay in constant execution
to listen to you. For example, Apache,
okay? Apache is a service. Apache is
a service in that it
's nothing more than an executable, which is
permanently on and is
waiting for you to ask it for a
web page. And when you ask it for a web page,
at that moment it wakes up, at that
moment it gives you the web page and goes back
to sleep. Okay? Okay, let
's go.  Let's see in this case, eh, let's
see, let's see in this case that,
sorry, here we are not in process, we are not
going to threads, that at a given moment
we can work, because we have
multithreaded programming here, okay? Here
we can work with the creation of
different threads. That is, what I'm going to
do now is duplicate.
Let's see
here. Okay, we're going here. I'm going to leave
here. I'm going to
go to threads
exercises.
There are the 002 exercises.
is not multithreaded.
And now I say, I'm going to remove a few
zeros here,
okay?
Import,
okay? Print is not necessary.
Now it is equal to dat.
Now I
have it very clear. Printa now
no. Date time has no attribute. It doesn't
have one. Okay, let's see. Python daytime now.
Let's see. Python daytime current.
Okay. Geez, lache.
There,
now it is this
and now it is this.
Okay. Date time. No, no, no, no.
Seriously,
here. Okay. Okay. Let's  add one
more zero.
And
okay, how long did it take me?
start
end
print
took
longer str
eh end less start
more seconds
F5 Five.
Okay. And now everyone, pay attention to the
screen, okay? Because now the
fun begins. Now the fun begins in the
sense that what I'm going to do is going to
be awesome, but you have to
realize, okay? I think it'll be easy.
Okay, it took me 4 seconds.
16 times the same process.
So I come over here and say for e in
range that I have 16 cores. Well, 16.
I repeat this
16 times. Why? Because I have 16
cores. But doing that is going to help me
use all 16 cores.
The answer is no. The answer is
no because okay, it's there
calculating. Let's see how long it takes.
Because what I'm doing is what we've
done up until this
point, which is sequential programming.
And up to this point, it hasn't mattered
because the  The programs we've done up
until now were simple and
ran very fast, and we didn't really
notice
whether or not they were taking advantage of
all the cores. Because if any
program we've worked on up until now
took 0.005 seconds to run,
so what.
But now, especially in the era of
artificial intelligence, you know that, for
example, an
artificial intelligence training process can take
days or weeks. Okay? Good. After
repeating this process 16 times, it
tells me, I'm looking at the processor, it tells me it
took 65 seconds, that is, it
took 16 times the 4 seconds. And if I
look at the CPU, I'll see that I haven't used,
okay? All 16 cores. But instead,
And now comes the scary part. I'm going to
convert this for a moment.
Lie.
Okay, now 003.
I want to use multithreading.
Okay,
time I'm going.
Let's see.
Okay, so
let's pass it
here. I don't want
a second, a second
that I'm converting  No. Just
a second.
What I'm doing is asking
the GPT chat to do a conversion for me.
Okay, what I'm doing
is loading
a Python library called
Multiprocessing.
We're in multiprocessing.
We're going to load a library called
multiprocessing. We're using a
namespace. MP or whatever you want. And
from here we define what we
can know as a worker. That
is, in the
context of multiprocessing,
the worker is a bubble
where, from there, we're going to send that
bubble to each and every one of the
cores in the system.
So, from here, what I'm going to
do in this case is create what's
known as a process pool.
It's like throwing all the processes
into the pool at once, like saying, swimming in
parallel. And from there, what we're going
to do is execute them. If I now
execute this,
everyone's attention to the screen. I'll press F5.
Let's see the processor. Just a moment.
So, let's see, I don't understand.
Let's see, it's  starting up.
Let's see for a second because I should Let's
see, let's see, let's see, Where's the
shell?
Here. No, this is P. Okay, this is
something else.
No, I think it's fried.
Okay, I'm seeing what went
wrong here.
Let's see.
Okay, I'm going to in this specific case
I'm going to try a version optimized for
Linux.
Gee. Wait
a minute, because what print is there?
Print. No, no, no. Okay,
let's see,
if not,
if not now I'll try it with C.
Okay, I'm going to try it with C at least
to illustrate the process.
Exercises
multiprocess.cpp.
And now what I'm going to
do next is here
I'm going to open a terminal and I'm going to
compile.
Let's see,
let's go to multiprocess,
uh, G++
004.
output dot out.
Okay, let's execute output.
And where are you? Here. Okay. Well,
that's still not too much. I've seen.
Ah, no, no, no, wait, wait, wait, wait,
wait.  It's that peak right there.
Okay, let's see it.
Processes, iterations.
Well, more.
Let's add one more zero,
so this goes here,
this goes here,
and this goes here,
right? Okay, wait, now I've gone crazy. It
's... Ah, yes, it'll be one more. Okay, this
here, this
here. Okay, compile,
execute.
Now, what do you think?
Okay. And I'll stop.
Notice I had to increase it 10
times more and still, okay?
No, no, Fran, it's a very good
question. What the processor
basically does is distribute and create a
queue. So, if you launch 32 processes
against a 16-processor, it executes
16 and puts the other 16 in the queue. You have to keep
in mind that we don't
use the machine that closely; rather,
we're working against the
operating system, and the operating system
is the one that ultimately manages the
processor. So, when we do
this, now I add 10 times more.  I
compile, sorry,
I compile, I
execute.
Look at the processor.
And now what the processor is going to do
is, as
I told you, it's going to stay working at 100% for a couple of minutes. But what does working at 100% mean? Well, it means that instead of executing a process sequentially, that is, instead of calculating the same thing 16 times
one after the other, what it was
doing was calculating the same thing 16 times
in parallel, that is, launching a
process to each of the
system's cores.
The idea is this, okay? The idea is for you to
know that this can be done. I'm
working with multiprocessing, so
I imagine the next thing
you'd ask, Fran, is, okay, what about
the GPU? We'll talk
about the GPU later because, of course, if the processor
offers us opportunities to speed up the
process,
the GPU, as you can imagine,
offers us many more possibilities.
So, in a few weeks, what I
estimate I'll do is:  We'll be
working on exercises related
to Nvidia.
The thing is, I'm really afraid, let
's say, of working on exercises
related to the Nvidia API,
because that would mean that all of
you would have to have an
Nvidia graphics card, so, of course,
you'll say to me, "Well, maybe
not all of us have an Nvidia graphics card,
okay?" But anyway, just so you know.
Okay, from there, from there
we're going to talk about concurrency on the one hand
and on the other hand something that
seems even more terrifying to me. I'm going to go
to parallel programming and in the next few
days we'll work with
concurrent programming, but in the end obviously
we'll see.
Yes, yes, correct. In fact, no, if you've
noticed that a few cores have dropped
and then a few more have dropped
. Why? Well, because I asked for 16
processes, but of course, OBS is
running one process, Zoom will be
running another process. So, that's
correct. Indeed, the
operating system is the one that you  You say, "I want
16 cores." Through the operational study they
tell you, "Okay, I'll give you what I have and
what I don't have, I'll put it in the
queue and we'll see later."  Okay, so when
it came out,
I think it was
Windows Millennium, okay?  That the infamous
Windows Millennium was a time when
processors started having
two cores in the year 2000 and all that,
right?  There were some dual-core ones and
one thing happened and that is that with Windows
95 you could listen to music and do other
tasks because Windows 95 managed
multi-processing very well on a single
processor.  The same thing happened with Windows 98
, but with Windows Millennium they
screwed up and you would open music, start
working in Word and the music would cut out.
And you were like, wow, how is it possible
that this worked on Windows 95 and
Windows 98, but not on Windows
Millennium?  That the Millenium lasted two tor a day
.  Okay, that's why I'm telling you that
yes, the operating system does indeed
play a very important role
in what you ask for, but the
operating system already looks to see what it
can give you.  Okay,
okay.  Uh, with parallel and
distributed programming.
This is where it's going to
blow your mind next, okay?  Because I
propose the following.
A processor
has x cores.  This processor has
16 cores.  But if I go to a classroom
where there are, for example, 20 computers, I
could use 16 cores for 20
computers.  Therefore, it could use
power cores.
How would you say I
can take advantage of the fact that I can make an
application that uses 320 cores of
power?
So let's
start working on this
issue
and on the one hand we're going to start
working with distributed programming.
distributed means distributing across
a series of computers and then
later we will work with
network communications.  Today we are going to work a little
with network communications.  Okay, let's move on to
parallel and distributed programming, and
for that, I'm going to come here
and take a look for a moment.
Programming
in speech and distributed and 002
exercises.
Okay,
for that,
oh, this is this is data access.
This is true.  Okay.  Spoken and
distributed programming.
Exercises.  Very good.  001.
Let's see, Fran, damn, you saw me there
.  Socket server.  Indeed,
that is the answer.  Okay, well, that's
an answer, that's a good answer.
Wait a minute.  Wait a minute.
Wait a minute.  Ah.
Ah.   I
don't understand.
Okay.
Okay, one second,
one second, one second.  No.
Okay,
okay, so uh
yeah, yeah, correct.  Okay, the topic of the
topic of the sockets.  Okay, so
here we go.  So okay, at that
time it was indeed with
Blender.
Let's see, let's
see,
on the one hand we're going to make a program
that's going to do, eh,
no,
no, no.  Just a moment, just a moment, just a
moment, I've lost my temper.   Let's
see, what it's
going to do is listen and what it's
going to do is put into service,
make a socket server available to the user
, okay?  To do this,
on the one hand, I'm going to have a
socket server, okay?, which is this one here,
importing the socket library.  We're going to
leave this here and in this case we're going
to link to IP 127001.
Okay,
having said that, well, on the port,
sorry, 1 2 3 4 5, because when we make
a network communication, we have to
specify which port
we want to listen on
and we enter a wi true.  We enter a
wi true in the sense that we enter
an infinite loop in which the server
is waiting.  F5 and the server is
waiting.  Okay, now
I'm going to start another IDLE next.
In IDL I'm going to start a
blank file and create a client.
So I go back to the folder,
I go back to the folder,
I go
to DAM 2526, I
go to second, I go to
service and process scheduling, multiprocessing for
now, parallel and distributed.
exercises and socket client,
okay?  So, so if I do this now
,
if I do this now, let's see.
Okay,
so this is the client socket and this
is the server socket.
This out.
This is the client
here, huh?  Oh, okay, yeah, sorry.  Socket
server here.  Now yes.  Okay, Socket
client here.
And the client says, "I've connected to the
server, hello, to the server."  And the
client says, "I received from the
server, hello to the server."
This means that when
we have a socket server and a
socket client,
we can communicate with
applications
and we can send information so that a
remote computer can compute that information and
return it to the main computer.
So if we have a server
we can have as many clients as we
want.  We're going to run
some kind of calculation
a bit like what you're talking about, right?  Like the
Blender network client thing for distributed rendering, but
simpler, right?  But perform
calculations.
So in this case I'm going to do the
following.  Let's see.
Here what I'm going to do is calculate,
let's see, 1000 times a number.
Socket object, okay?
Okay.
Hello Server, no
good.  Hello Server.
This is the client.
Let's see,
because now what I want is for the
client to be the one who calculates.
Okay,
the server is going to say,
"Okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay
, okay, okay."  Okay, the server is going
to say number
equals 1.004
times equals 10 billion
trillion.
So what I want in this case is to
send the data
on the connection.
Okay,
look, I'm going to create
a dictionary
and in the dictionary I'm going to put all
this in the form of a dictionary
so I can send it.  The question is, am I
going to be able to send a dictionary to
a socket?
Maybe yes, maybe not, but if I can't
send you a dictionary, I'll tell you
now that the solution will be to
serialize it, serialize it with what
we saw in the previous subject.
Okay, I want to send
what is data.
Okay, okay.  I want to send the dictionary
received from the server.
Server receipt.
So I run the server,
I run the client, okay?  Byt.  That's
the problem.  So what have we done
before?  Well, before we did
import j
what we do is a moment I'll tell you
here jon.domp
dictionary.
This is the server.  Hey, watch out.  Oh,
wow.  Another thing, when our
socket server hangs,
the port hangs.  Okay, I'm going to use
port 1 2 3 4 6.
Here I'm going to use port 1 2 3 4 6.
Yeah,
okay.  Server client.  OK.  Dom. Ah,
sorry, sorry.
Json.
No,
let's see what you recommend.
Oh, wow.
We are.  Ok, F5 and already inuse.
What a bummer.
F5
F5 Okay.
Bytes like object is not required not a
string.
Well,
let's see if I can pass on the information.
Okay,
that's a good question.  Okay, now
we talk about that.  Obviously, wait
a minute.  Obviously the answer
to what you asked is yes.  I mean,
in any case, I'm really pissed off about
the network address.
In any case, the
comparison between Python and no dejs, no
dejs is always going to fly.
Okay, now yes.  What have I received from the
server?
I have received these from server number 1,004
times here.  What does this
mean?  Well, now I'll
decode data and what I can do now
is important
and in the client I'm going to say, eh J is not
good, let's see the data, it's equal to
data pun decode or jonlo loads
data dot decode print
data. I hope it
doesn't tell me that it's in use.  Thank
goodness.  I say F5 and if you notice,
I receive this from the server here and
convert it to JSON.  And if I convert it to
JSON, then on the client, for
example, I can start a process in
which it calculates, I don't know how many times
one number is multiplied by another.
I mean, I can
send information, right?, within a
single computer.  In this case I am on a
single computer because I am in an
office where I am alone.  Okay?
But obviously it could go, we could
in fact even
do it for the exams that you
have to come in person, do an experiment of sending a different package to each computer and making sure that if there are 20 computers in the classroom, we distribute a computation across 20 different computers.
Okay?  Now,
going to the question you asked, Fran,
uh, the point is that we
already know that Python is actually
slower than the bad guy's horse.  C++
is very fast, but for doing
complex things it's a pain in the ass, right?
DJS is a pretty good middle ground,
as we've seen in years, well, in
previous years, last year, okay?
We know that NDJS, being based on
JavaScript, is very easy to
use, and we know, and we have compared it
previously last year, that the
difference in power and performance
with Python is very, very nice, right?
So effectively a
perfect alternative for this would be
NOD JS.  Okay, I'm going to wrap things up a little bit,
okay?  We
might end up around 9:15, 9:20
so Serena doesn't kill me.
We'll continue tomorrow. Obviously, you already
know that tomorrow, if we look at the
calendar,
we have an
intermodular project class at 1:30 and a
business management systems class at 3:00.
Okay?
So, uh, questions.
Tomorrow we'll also talk about how
the assignment submission process works this year
.  I'll tell you that this year,
where the idea is to organize everything in
terms of teaching units and
teaching subunits, we're going to go to the
second one. I'll tell you that in
programming, for example, of processes and
services or in data access or in
any subject, the idea is
unit one.  There will be an exercise to
do from unit 1. Subunit 1 1.
There will be an exercise to do from
subunit 1 1. Unit 1 subunit 2.
unit 1 subunit two, okay?  There will be an
exercise to perform for each of
the units and subunits in which we
have worked.  And that
exercise is going to be personalized
based on the questionnaire I sent you the
other day, which I'll send you tomorrow.  ask
if you have filled out the questionnaire
and then tomorrow we will also talk about
how to submit that form.
Remember how to hand in those
exercises.  Remember that in the
documents the other day I left you the
evaluation rubric where the
evaluation rubric includes the
instructions on how to answer
the exercises, okay? I'll
add them to you.
Tomorrow we will talk about this in
impersonal management systems and in
intermodular projects.  And nothing, and that's it, okay?
So you'll see that this year I'm going to
present you with a very standardized way of
performing the exercises and presenting
the results.  By the way, I want to tell you that
this evaluation rubric you're
seeing is the same one you'll
find on the exams.  That is,
once you get the hang of this
assessment rubric, the
entire course in the subjects
with me, obviously, with other
teachers, well, I can't force them to
use this system, but all the
subjects with me,
units, subunits and exam will be
exactly the same.  Okay?  So,
you'll see that once you get the
hang of it, it's just fill, fill, fill,
and fill.
Tomorrow we will do, we will do
demonstrations.  By the way, I was
remembering a question that
Ángel, Ángel, Miguel Ángel asked me before
about, uh, not only last year's videos
, but last year's code.
Keep one thing in mind, Miguel Ángel, and I'll
remind the rest of you too:
last year we weren't just working
on the DAM repository,
okay?  This repository here,
we put most of the exercises
there, but keep in mind that at some
point in the course we started
developing
HOCARSA applications.
Which means there are a lot
of applications
that are not in the main
DAM repository, but are in the
shadow repositories.  Okay?  I'm telling you, Miguel
Ángel, because you'll have to watch the videos,
especially starting in the second
quarter, to see when we
're working on each of the other
repositories, okay?  I also tell you
that all those repositories are
open in my Jithub account.  You can
come in, you can get the code, whatever
you want, okay?  You have it all, I mean,
you have it all and you all have it all
there so you can take it, take it and you
can and you can treat it and you can do
whatever you want.  Okay?  Okay, I'll tell you,
uh, tomorrow morning remember that
we have the intermodular project subject
from 1:30 to 2:30
and then comes, as I said, the
toughest and
most interesting subject of the second year, which
is business management systems.
That's the subject that's
going to give you the most work for obvious reasons, okay?
Because that's where we're going to learn to
develop and program
business management systems, which,
at least here in the
Valencia area, are the most popular jobs, right?
If we lived in Silicon Valley,
MySQL would probably give us money, while Oracle would,
in other words, hire us to program
databases.
If we lived in Betón, in
California, okay?  Well, OpenI would
hire us to do
multicore programming,
but we live in Valencia and basically
most of the money
is in programming
business management applications so
companies can make their moves.  So
, as I say, it is the
toughest and most interesting subject.
We're going to leave it here more or less today
, so tomorrow
we'll continue with the intermodular project.
The Apple clone.  Wait a minute.   What do you mean
by Apple?  No, no, no, no, no,
no.  Okay, no, no.  Last year we did
the project of,
I'm trying to remember the name,
it was a wheat-colored thing or something like that.
Okay, so we made a clone of the
Apple page and then made a dashboard for it
.  Okay?  Would you refer more to the
control panel?
No, it's much further.  Okay, so
last year what we did was almost a
kind of, quote unquote,
WordPress clone.
But WordPress isn't a
business management system, it's a
content management system.  And the
content management system, well, yes, well, it's
a small part of a
business management system, right?  The goal is to
manage invoices, customers, orders,
accounting, human resources,
production, right?  It's what we did
last year with the control panel, I think it
was Light Late Blue, but it was really
extensive, and we have a whole subject
to do it, and it's, as I said, the
most important subject in the second
year.  So yes, there is
indeed a part, Fran, of
growing module by module.  Look at
what I'm telling you, Fran. In fact, if I
look at the syllabus,
you'll see that in business management systems,
specifically point
number five, teaching unit five,
is component development, that is,
modular development so that, starting
from a base development, we can
add modules that expand the
functionality.  So, what you
're saying is, in fact, in
line with the official syllabus.  I'm
telling you, it's not a syllabus that
I made, it's the official syllabus that comes with the
department, okay?  Correct, correct.
Well, that's the point we're going to make
in this course:
preparing ourselves for the code so that we
know that it's not just that what
we program isn't already there, but that whatever
we program is safe for the future,
so that we can continue to grow it.
Okay?  Well, that's all for today.   I'll
stop the recording here and see you later.